<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lucy Bain</title>
  <id>http://lucybain.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://lucybain.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://lucybain.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Lucy Bain</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Recommended Reading</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/recommended-reading/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/recommended-reading/</id>
    <published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the years I’ve recommended these books to many people. Each one has changed how I approach my work, those around me, and myself. The list is unordered, each book was impactful at one point in my life, and the order you choose to read them depends where you are in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve included amazon links to each of the books to make them easier to find and read reviews from others. These aren’t affiliate links; they’re just there for ease, not money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Secret Thoughts of Successful Women&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Secret-Thoughts-Successful-Women-Impostor-ebook/dp/B004KPM1N0"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; is all about impostor syndrome; why we feel it, how to recognise it, ways to deal with it. I found it very grounding to hear other women’s experiences and recognise that I’m not alone. For me, The Secret Thoughts of Successful Women was more practically helpful than &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Confidence-Code-Science-Self-Assurance-What-Should/dp/006223062X"&gt;The Confidence Code&lt;/a&gt;. But people are different, so you might want to checkout this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s written with women in mind, I believe men experiencing impostor syndrome would find value in it. (If you have a male specific version of this book to recommend please do let me know!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Presence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might remember the author, Amy Cuddy, from her immensely popular &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_may_shape_who_you_are/transcript?language=en"&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt;. If you liked that 20 minute version, you’ll love her whole &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Presence-Bringing-Boldest-Biggest-Challenges/dp/140915601X/ref=asc_df_140915601X/"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally advice about being more confident comes down to “fake it till you make it.” But Dr Cuddy’s book covers the practical details of how to fake it, at least for your body language. I thought this was so interesting and directly useful I gave a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YTHeJdKN9Ks"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Assertiveness Workbook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is a bit different because it’s a &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Assertiveness-Workbook-Express-Yourself-Relationships/dp/1572242094"&gt;workbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. There are exercises throughout the book, and space to write your answers. I recommend getting a physical copy so you can interact with it easily. Reading this book cover to cover is easy enough, but if you take the time to do the exercises you’ll get so much more out of it. That said, it’s hard work and can be emotionally draining. Give yourself plenty of time to go through it. For me, this workbook helped me bring a more authentic self to the table. It helped me stand up for what I wanted without feeling that I needed to apologise for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Life-Changing Magic of Tidying Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this is a strange recommendation, but this &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Life-Changing-Magic-Tidying-Decluttering-Organizing/dp/1607747308"&gt;little book&lt;/a&gt; really did make a difference for me. A core concept of the Konmari method is constantly asking “does this spark joy?” Things that don’t spark joy you thank and get rid of. First you practice with your clothes, then you move on more difficult items in your house. After awhile I found that I asked the same question of many aspects in my life. Would going to this event bring me joy? What about today’s work was the least joyful? The most? When am I deeply satisfied with my experiences and life? Building up this muscle to be able to evaluate choices based on joy rather than social expectations made a big difference to me. &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Curated-Closet-Discovering-Personal-Building/dp/1607749483"&gt;The Curated Closet&lt;/a&gt; is along similar lines, although not as focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Gifts of Imperfection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Gifts-Imperfection-Brene-Brown/dp/1785043544/ref=sr_1_2?crid=270N6ZZJY1AYW&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=brene+brown&amp;amp;qid=1622946799&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sprefix=brene%2Cstripbooks%2C327&amp;amp;sr=1-2"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; came from a friend’s recommendation (thanks Tracy!). It talks a lot about “wholehearted” living, which I think of as being authentic, even when it’s difficult to do so. It deals with deep topics such as guilt, shame, and self-worth, and discusses ways to deal with emotions and difficulties in this area. It can also be quite a hard book to go through; there are exercises at the end of each chapter helping you focus on specific areas in your life and consider how to be more wholehearted in each one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>One-on-One Meeting Template</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/one-on-one-template/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/one-on-one-template/</id>
    <published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a manager for over four years now, and I still really enjoy it. I thought I should share some of the tools I’ve used with others and hopefully get some feedback as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I schedule my one-on-ones (1:1s) for 30 minutes every week, but the template would work for other frequencies or durations as well. Some managers don’t take notes during 1:1s - this might work well if you have a small team and a fast performance review cycle (and a great memory!). However my team is anywhere from 6-12 people, and our official review cycle is annual (and I don’t have the best memory...). So I make sure to take and notes about each 1:1. This is the template I use to my team member and me on the same page (literally!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/blog/one-on-one-template/template-c742fc8c.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I have four columns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date - when we had the 1:1. I put the additional table cells on the page one month at a time, so either of us can fill in future meetings with notes to add if needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their column - their space to write whatever agenda items they want to cover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My column - my space to add agenda items&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action items - a checklist of things we need to do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a terribly interesting template, but it works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 1:1 we work from left to right. Any agenda item in their column trumps my agenda items. If we run out of time we can schedule another session. If we repeatedly run out of time we can increase our default duration. This means some team members have two 1:1s in a specific week. I’ve also setup some team members with regular 45 minute 1:1s; typically this happens when we&amp;#39;re working on a promotion case or they’re running a complex project and it doesn’t last forever (but it’s fine if it does!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we talk, I add details about the agenda items they added to their column (or take live notes on what they discussed but wasn’t on the page in advance). Since we both have access to the page, this means they can review my notes and let me know if I misunderstood or misinterpreted something they said. I try to jot down notes for what I said too (if the agenda item isn’t clear enough), but I’ll admit I don’t always get this right. It’s hard to talk and type at the same time! A few people will take notes on their own, but I don’t enforce this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically towards the end of the meeting we’ll summarise any actions either of us need to take and keep track of it in the “Action items” column. Each item should have an assignee, and it’s ok if things are assigned to me. I want to make it clear that it’s fine for them to expect me to get things done. We have different roles and responsibilities. I need to meet mine just as much as they need to meet theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run this template for one year, covering the same time period as the annual review. I’ve tried having each session on a different page, but it means you can’t easily &lt;code&gt;cmd+f&lt;/code&gt; for topics that you’re pretty sure you covered earlier. Depending on your review cycle it might make sense to split out the pages for 3 or 6 months just to keep things tidier.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Free Coaching Sessions Again!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-sessions-pt2/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-sessions-pt2/</id>
    <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I offered to coach four women over six months. It&amp;#39;s been such an interesting and rewarding experience that I&amp;#39;m doing it again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m particularly interested in &lt;strong&gt;coaching women tech managers&lt;/strong&gt;. This is open to current managers, or individual contributors who are strongly considering a move into management. “Tech” roles can include a variety of positions: developers, designers, project managers, quality engineers, content writers, etc. Please still apply if you’re keen, but don’t particularly align with one of these specific roles. These were just the ones that came to mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bit about coaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people have never had a coaching session, so it’s hard to know what to expect. Coaching allows you to talk through a problem with someone who isn’t also trying to talk through their problem, prove how smart they are, or in charge of your salary. We’ll reflect on a particular problem you’ve brought. I’ll ask more questions than I answer, and you’ll do most of the thinking and talking. Then I’ll help you frame an action plan and some goals for the next session. I’ve also got another &lt;a href="/blog/2021/coaching-session-prep"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about how to prep and some rough timing for the session. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Details:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One hour each&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once roughly every three weeks (July - November)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expect homework each session, around an hour a week or less&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free! Kind of...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;“Payment”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don&amp;#39;t want your money - I want to help you and give back to our wonderful community! However, to make this work you need to be as committed as I am. The best way I know to quantify commitment between strangers is with money. So here are the rules for payment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pay $300 upfront that I&amp;#39;ll hold, but not spend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ll transfer you $50 back after every session you attend. That way you get the whole amount if you show up for all six sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you reschedule with less than 12 hours notice I will keep $25 to offset the annoyance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you simply don&amp;#39;t show up then I keep the full $50. Again, I&amp;#39;d rather do the session, but if I gave up my evening sitting on a video call alone then I&amp;#39;d like to get my nails done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve done this kind of payment before and have a track record of not stealing from anyone. The initial payment wouldn&amp;#39;t be due until after our “get to know you” session - don’t give money to strangers on the internet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If $300 is prohibitively expensive for you (student, unemployed, etc) please mention this in your application and we’ll figure something out. Again - I don’t want your money, I want your commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Apply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify as a woman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tech related role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently a manager (or strongly considering it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Available for sessions during the evening AEDT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good enough internet connection for an hour long video call&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sessions in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications due by June 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdQhhjugyT-wIfMKzmw4n6KHAQE3AFIgpqtTT4kCeFnVOD22A/viewform?usp=sf_link"&gt;Apply here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll contact everyone during the last week of June. I&amp;#39;ll schedule a 30 min “get to know you” session to double check that we want to commit to this process together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Additional info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a bit more about me, so you know what I have experience with and where I might help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed a computer science degree in the US; some friends have done coding bootcamps, but I don&amp;#39;t have first hand experience here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lived and worked in Silicon Valley for a couple of years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved to New Zealand and then Sydney (covering visa stress, feeling like an outsider, and settling in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worked for a couple of small startups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now work for Atlassian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved from developer to manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been involved in the community over the years, working with: Women Who Code Sydney, Rails Girls, Girl Geek Dinners, and run a few programming related study groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also have a passion for public speaking, especially for new or hesitant speakers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preparing for our coaching session</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-session-prep/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-session-prep/</id>
    <published>2021-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is written mostly for the four women who are part of my community &lt;a href="/blog/2021/coaching-sessions/"&gt;coaching program&lt;/a&gt;. It will mostly apply to anyone doing coaching with me, and might be helpful to review before a coaching session with others as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pre-work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before each session take some time to think about a problem or area of your life that you’d like to discuss. The topic should be job related, but can leak into your personal life as well. It shouldn’t be something fact based like “how to fix this bug” but maybe “I have trouble speaking up in meetings” or “my boss doesn’t give me challenging work.” Part of the coaching process includes taking time to understand and clarify the topic so it doesn’t need to be super well defined yet! Personally, I usually think about what’s been my biggest difficulty in the past 2-4 weeks and talk through that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;difficulty communicating with a particular team member&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;struggling with work life balance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thinking about leaving your company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having trouble jumping into conversations on Zoom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have an hour booked with me to learn, grow, and plan for your future. I’ll keep an eye on the time to make sure we don’t go over, but the time is yours. That being said, the timing often works out roughly like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25 minutes to better understand the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25 minutes to discuss and plan out a plan of attack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 minutes to review, give feedback, and wrap up the session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We won’t stick to that exactly, but I hope it’s helpful to have an idea of what you’re walking into!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Homework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, during our session you’ll come up with a plan to enact over the next month. Where desired, please do the work or make relevant changes to the plan works better for you as needed. Ideally this is an exciting assignment as you work on yourself and your career!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the session or in an email after, I might suggest some exercises or reading that I believe would be valuable for you. Please dedicate up to an hour a week to these assignments, but don’t let them take away from your main plan for the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not everyone is ready to “do” after just one discussion. Your plan might fall to the bottom of your to do list or feel unapproachable after our session. If this is the case please be honest with me in our next meeting. What held you back? What were you most dreading? Please be thoughtful; “I didn’t have time” is usually not the root reason. If we can approach the situation without shame or judgment we’re more likely to make progress in the next session.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2021 Coaching Sessions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-sessions/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2021/coaching-sessions/</id>
    <published>2021-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to 2021!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I&amp;#39;ll give back to the amazing community in a different, covid safe, way. I&amp;#39;m offering four people six coaching sessions! I got a lot of value attending coaching sessions; so much so, that I took a course on how to be a coach so I could help others. I really liked the one-on-one focus, and ability to dive deep into a problem with someone else. I&amp;#39;d like to take my coaching practice deeper through a continued relationship so you have time to make changes and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m particularly interested in &lt;strong&gt;coaching women through inflection points&lt;/strong&gt;. Did you become a manager? Or perhaps you&amp;#39;re considering changing companies? Are you a mid or senior developer wondering how to have wider impact? Possibly you&amp;#39;re a junior developer in your first programming job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do apply if you&amp;#39;re keen, but don&amp;#39;t particularly align with one of these inflection points. These were just the ones that came to mind, but I&amp;#39;m happy to hear about other situations too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Details:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One hour each&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once a month (February - July)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expect homework each session, around an hour a week or less&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free! Kind of...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&amp;quot;Payment&amp;quot;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don&amp;#39;t want your money - I want to help you and give back to our wonderful community! However, to make this work you need to be as committed as I am. The best way I know to quantify commitment between strangers is with money. So here are the rules for payment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pay $300 upfront that I&amp;#39;ll hold, but not spend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ll transfer you $50 back after every session you attend. That way you get the whole amount if you show up for all six sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you reschedule with less than 12 hours notice I will keep $25 to offset the annoyance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you simply don&amp;#39;t show up then I keep the full $50. Again, I&amp;#39;d rather do the session, but if I gave up my evening sitting on a video call alone then I&amp;#39;d like to get my nails done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve done this kind of payment before and have a track record of not stealing from anyone. The initial payment wouldn&amp;#39;t be due until after our &amp;quot;get to know you&amp;quot; session - don&amp;#39;t give money to strangers on the internet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If $300 is prohibitively expensive for you (student, unemployed, etc) please mention this in your application and we&amp;#39;ll figure something out. Again - I don&amp;#39;t want your money, I want your commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Apply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify as a woman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Available for sessions during the evening AEDT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good enough internet connection for an hour long video call&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sessions in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications due by Jan 14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdQhhjugyT-wIfMKzmw4n6KHAQE3AFIgpqtTT4kCeFnVOD22A/viewform?usp=sf_link"&gt;Apply here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll contact everyone during the last week of January. I&amp;#39;ll schedule a 30 min &amp;quot;get to know you&amp;quot; session to double check that we want to commit to this process together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Additional info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a bit more about me, so you know what I have experience with and where I might help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed a computer science degree in the US; some friends have done coding bootcamps, but I don&amp;#39;t have first hand experience here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lived and worked in Silicon Valley for a couple of years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved to New Zealand and then Sydney (covering visa stress, feeling like an outsider, and settling in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worked for a couple of small startups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now work for Atlassian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved from developer to manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been involved in the community over the years, working with: Women Who Code Sydney, Rails Girls, Girl Geek Dinners, and run a few programming related study groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also have a passion for public speaking, especially for new or hesitant speakers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Three tips for reports to improve one-on-ones: Part 1</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2019/better-one-on-ones-pt1/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2019/better-one-on-ones-pt1/</id>
    <published>2019-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having better one-on-ones (1:1s) is usually left up to the manager. There are &lt;a href="https://www.atiim.com/blog/use-these-6-rules-to-build-better-one-on-ones/"&gt;loads&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.officevibe.com/blog/guide-to-better-one-on-ones"&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/how-to-have-oneonones-that-actually-matter"&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.booktopia.com.au/radical-candor-kim-scott-malone/prod9781509845385.html"&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.booktopia.com.au/management-stephen-robbins/prod9781488609077.html"&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; written with the manager in mind. But focusing exclusively on only one of the attendees drastically reduces how useful the meeting can be. In this post I’ll focus on ways that the team member (report) can improve a 1:1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your 1:1s have &lt;em&gt;improved&lt;/em&gt; if you get more &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; out of the meetings. A 1:1 can be “bad” in that you received criticism during the meeting. However it can still be &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt; in that the feedback helped you be better at your job. Similarly a 1:1 can be “good” in that you and your manager had a nice chat. However a 1:1 like that might not be &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt; in that you and your manager might already have a pretty solid relationship. (Yes, I know having “just a chat” can be valuable from time to time, but if that’s all you’re doing it’s unlikely that the relationship is helping you with your job.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tips below set a decent baseline. Many of you are probably already doing all of these things - that’s great! Some of you will find starting with these three tips to be challenging enough for now - that’s great too! I’ll add some more posts with tips later on. These suggestions should continue to increase how much value you get from your 1:1s, and will be a little more difficult than the tips below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Actually have the meeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think back over the past six months, have you and your manager met regularly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a 1:1 calendar slot already then add one in. Pick a regular time to meet with your manager. Make sure that time usually works for them. Add a calendar event and invite them to it. Frequency varies a lot, so I recommend starting with every other week and adjusting from there. If having 1:1s at all is unusual at your company you might want to try for 30 minutes once a month and increase the frequency as you’re able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have a meeting setup but don&amp;#39;t actually &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; the meeting. Occasional misses are generally ok (people get sick and go on holidays), but if the meeting is skipped more than 25% of the time then it’s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are canceling then evaluate why that is and try to make a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are the meetings at a bad time? Ask your manager if you can shift to a different time. Give a suggestion about when works better for you (in the morning right after standup, at 11:30 just before lunch, etc) and ideally check their calendar to make sure they’re free at the time you’re suggesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you feel you have to get your work done and don’t have time for a meeting? Have an explicit conversation with your manager whenever you bail for this reason. Perhaps they agree with you in this particular situation (ideally you can reschedule) or perhaps they haven’t made the priorities clear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you not get value from the meetings? Keep reading! Make some changes and give them another chance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your &lt;em&gt;manager&lt;/em&gt; is canceling the 1:1s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consider that having 1:1s with you is part of your managers job. You have a right to expect these meetings just as much as they have a right to expect you do your job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raise it with them. This is hard. I won’t judge you if you don’t go down this path. Ideally you can ask them why they keep canceling and come up with a solution. Perhaps your manager thinks you’re doing so well you don’t need regular meetings! Whatever the reason letting them know you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to meet at least helps set expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raise it with their boss. Again difficult, but possibly easier than speaking directly to your manager. Perhaps your manager has too much going on but they haven’t been able to bring it up with their boss yet. Possibly they think they’re meeting with you more frequently than they really are (they have a lot of meetings, it’s easy to forget). Whatever the reason, raising this with their boss can give feedback and context and hopefully help your situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Talk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your manager is asking questions they want the answers! Answer with something more than just yes or no. If you need to, ask for some time to think over what your answer will be and respond at a later date (if this happens a lot ask them to share their questions in advance where possible). Awkward silences signal that you probably don’t want to be there - and it’s just as awkward for your manager as for you. Ideally bring something to contribute to the conversation as well, which brings us to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Prepare for your 1:1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before your next 1:1 take some time to think about what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; want to talk about. This doesn’t need to be a big ordeal, you can start with just 5 minutes. As you get more comfortable with it, you can take notes on what you’d like to discuss any time between meetings. Many people have a 1:1 page to jot down notes about what you’d like to discuss in your next meeting. Bonus points if you share this page with your manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggested prompts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want some feedback? Ideally ask for feedback on something specific rather than an open ended “do you have any feedback for me?” Yes, asking for general feedback is ok too, but you’ll probably get better quality feedback if you ask for it on a particular topic. You’ll get even better feedback if you let your boss know you’ll be asking for that feedback in advance!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you like some advice? Maybe you’ve had a difficult personal interaction, perhaps your work took longer to get reviewed than you would have liked, possibly you’re uncertain about how to get started with your next piece of work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s something you’ve done well? 1:1s are a great time to highlight your accomplishments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have some insights into your team? What do you see that your manager might have missed? Maybe someone took the time to explain a new concept to you, perhaps you’re concerned about friction between team members, possibly your recent retrospective got you thinking about a new process you’d like to try out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are things progressing on your project? Are you happy with the quality you’re producing or do you need more time to better plan the work? What process might need changing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can your manager change to help you and the team? Your manager probably doesn’t get a lot of feedback from their reports - a 1:1 can be a good time give them some.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have regular 1:1s with your manager, start by setting one up. From there you can work on having deeper and more useful conversations during your meetings. Regular time with you manager can be really helpful. These meetings can be even more valuable if you contribute too!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
