<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lucy Bain</title>
  <id>http://lucybain.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://lucybain.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://lucybain.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Lucy Bain</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Ela Conf - morning of day two</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/ela-conf-day-2/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/ela-conf-day-2/</id>
    <published>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T17:20:48-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We started with a light breakfast and moved right into the talks. Again, so many positive vibes and happy voices. Everyone is clearly excited to be here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off with some stories from the organisers about how they got into tech and why they decided to work with Ela Conf. It&amp;#39;s always nice to hear people’s stories and better understand where the conference comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Welcome to day two!" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/welcome-day-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Five things I Leared About Leadership from my Son, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rockchick322004"&gt;Mary Scotton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get your hands dirty - be completely involved in, and committed to, your work. Other people will notice that you’re willing to get shit done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the rules - a.k.a. don’t do what your told. Your job isn’t just to do what you’re told, it’s to think, make considered decisions, and build good stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to coffee - spending authentic time with people (in and out of work) builds community and your network. Make an effort to keep moving relationships forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respect other perspectives - as a leader, it’s your job to make work a safe place to share different ideas. This is related to gender/race/etc. diversity, but it’s more about diversity of thought and allowing others to open up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be you - if you’re holding yourself back you’re not able to fully do the above and connect with people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Never Accept the First Offer, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WhataTiberius"&gt;Tiberius Hefflin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay gap between women and men still exists. Companies can help by doing pay auditing (Atlassian does this - yay!), having blind applications, and setting up rules to favour people asking for more information around pay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start small on things you don’t care about so you can get used to the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do your research before you start negotiating - what really is a &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;/em&gt; offer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a list of your skills are and what you bring to the table. This can help keep you focused and remind you why you’re asking for what you’re asking for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask for a pay review in six months so you have time to show them what you’re worth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Respect Effect, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TimirahJ"&gt;Timirah James&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to teach people how to treat you, and what you will and won’t put up with. Make it clear when you don’t feel respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat yourself the way you want others to treat you - this effect works from the inside out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way that you’re perceived is something you can change, but you have to be mindful of it all the time - this takes effort!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Get yourself a squad!, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nicolelzhu"&gt;Nicole Zhu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Coding is not a skill that you just innately have.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staying&lt;/em&gt; in tech is much harder than starting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A squad is there to support you and your work - they’re friends who have the context of your work experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your friends can give you more authentic feedback and keep you energized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mulan’s Squad" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/squad.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tell Your Story: Crafting An Authentic Elevator Pitch That Works (workshop), by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tmasphilly"&gt;Hillary Rea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Leadership and management (panel)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s all about communication - listening to your team members and getting them to open up about difficulties they’re experiencing, give time for others to offer suggestions before jumping in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:1s should be more than just status checks; ask about life and future roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re wondering about moving to leadership, think about your current job: what kinds parts do you enjoy the most? (Coding vs. working with people vs. strategy meetings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Script difficult conversations (and practice with easy conversations!) so you know what you’re going to say and can stay calm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotating roles (like scrum master) so others in the team can know what’s involved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AlexandraLash/status/794970525642719233"&gt;&lt;img alt="Leadership and management" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/leadership-sketch-notes.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources mentioned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thebroadexperience.com/"&gt;The broad experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://larahogan.me/blog/"&gt;Lara Hogan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rands in Repose &lt;a href="http://randsinrepose.com/welcome-to-rands-leadership-slack/"&gt;leadership slack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Value of “I Don’t Know”, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/not_pele"&gt;Elise Wei&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saying “I don’t know” helps fight imposter syndrome and makes others more comfortable with being honest about what they know too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t just ask for the answer, ask &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; they found the answer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Builds up a culture of learning - you can encourage others to admit when they don’t know something and all learn together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It’s not you, it’s them. What next?, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/theOnlyRuthie"&gt;Ruthie Floats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s all about feelings. Your salary doesn’t actually matter, it’s how you feel about your salary that really matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the feeling, then the cause, then come up with an action. “I feel (blank) because (blank). So I will (blank).”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What feelings are you hoping to get out of working in open source? Look for open source projects that meet these needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="It’s not you" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/its-them.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Getting Involved and Giving Back As A Beginner, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/_lisli"&gt;Lisa Yoder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document what you know, what you’re learning, and what you’re struggling with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep lists of things you did that were hard - refer to these when you need a boost (like my moments of win list!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noobs often explain things better since they just recently learned it. “You can be an expert at being a beginner.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Take up space: claiming your place in tech, by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adriennefriend"&gt;Adrienne Lowe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show yourself the same compassion you would show others (kinda a reverse golden rule)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celebrate the little wins too since they’re practice for celebrating the big wins; these wins help fight imposter syndrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Asking for help when you need it is standing up for yourself.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s a difference between &lt;em&gt;real life&lt;/em&gt; struggle (food, safety, belonging, opening up to others), and &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; struggle. Take a deep breath and understand the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference to &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00L0F01NK/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;btkr=1"&gt;We should all be feminists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Naomi_Donna/status/794998786301063168"&gt;&lt;img alt="Take up space" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/take-up-space.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ela Conf - day one</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/ela-conf-day-1/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/ela-conf-day-1/</id>
    <published>2016-11-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T09:19:54-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friday night was for talks and Lightning Talks. It was pretty quick, 7-8:30 or so, but a great way to meet some of my fellow attendees and kick off the good vibes for the evening. Props to the organisers who required all of the lightning talk presenters to send their slides in a couple hours before tonight started - that extra bit of planning made the evening so much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Welcome!" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/welcome-day-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Build Your Community to Build Your Career, by Eleanor Whitney&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what you have can bring to the table. You have skills and a history other people are interested in - which skills? what stories? How can you best share these?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community is part of your intellectual property (not sure I agree with this, but interesting idea)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scared of joining communities? Be human - you’re not alone. (Sounds like my “You’re not a snowflake”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel free to ask for help from your community, but be sure to help other members as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5 Ways to Increase Your Influence, by Elizabeth Brown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reciprocity - if you help someone they’re more likely to help you in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liking principle - people want to help people they like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ben Franklin Effect - getting a rejection, probably means you’ll get a yes from them in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scarcity - make it clear that you’re not permanently available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Body language - project confidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information from &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Influence-Practice-Robert-B-Cialdini/dp/0205609996"&gt;Influence: science and practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Increasing influence" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/increase-influence.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Angry Black Woman, by Brittany Canty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holding back your emotions doesn’t always help; other people need to see how what they’re saying actual impacts you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It takes a lot of effort and energy to hold yourself back, instead use the energy for something better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Being angry is ok" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/angry-black-woman.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5 Stages of Accepting Negative Feedback, by Jessica Hall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denial - there’s no way that’s true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger - why don’t they get it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consideration - maybe they’ve got a point, or we were wrong; is there a pattern or was it a once off?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panic - how do you actually improve? How do you improve fast enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excitement - yay! You know more, and things can get better!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seek out negative feedback, and thank the people who have the courage to give it to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Scope Creep: Keep It From Creeping Up On You, by Angelina Simms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We usually only think of scope creep as applying to software. But sometimes &lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt; creeps up on you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What systems do you have in place to manage scope creep in your life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set things up to deal with life&amp;#39;s scope creep &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; things come up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Shaving my head made me a better programmer, by Alex Qin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being asked at university “Are you a programmer?” and replying “Well, not really, but I’m trying to become one.” Realising that this doesn’t make sense because “the act of programming makes you a programmer.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Become a bad ass programmer and they can’t doubt your programming abilities.” - Alex went for it, and started giving lots of talks and putting her ideas out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screw it - shaved her hair and &lt;em&gt;boom&lt;/em&gt; community members and coworkers started treating her as a legit programmer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wanted to help others who “shouldn’t be programmers,” founded &lt;a href="http://www.c4q.nyc/"&gt;Coalition for Queens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can succeed if they have the right resources, and people believe in them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No hair == better programmer" src="/images/blog/ela-conf/shaved-head.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Attending Vogue Codes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/vogue-codes/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/vogue-codes/</id>
    <published>2016-10-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-25T02:16:03-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago I was invited to attend Vogue Codes, an event for women in technology. I was lucky enough that my boss let me have the day off with almost no warning (thanks boss, and thanks Atlassian!). I was again lucky that my coworker told me she was going to wear a dress for the event, so I wore one too - this is the first tech conference where I would have felt weird wearing jeans and sneakers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Atlassian team!" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/vogue-team.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Overall impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vogue knows how to do glamor! I know this shouldn’t be surprising, but we had Wedgewood tea cups, beautiful table settings, and an embossed notebook at every seat. It was, by far, the girliest tech event I’ve ever been to. (And honestly, I loved it - I ran Classy Coding for Women Who Code which was a massively cheaper event, but in the same spirit.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Such a pretty venue" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/vogue-pretty.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So many women! There were ~15 tables of ~8 people each, so ~120 people at the event - almost all of them were women. I’ve been to similarly sized Girl Geek events, but never in so large a place. We took up the whole room, and there was a line for the bathroom. Very cool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="So many women" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/vogue-women.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So few programmers :( During the event someone asked us to raise our hand if we were in: media, PR, HR, etc. When they got to “programmers” I gleefully shot my hand up. My heart sank as I looked around the room at the other… 10? women with their hands up. Similarly, I did a rough check of how many of the speakers coded. Of the ~17 speakers guess how many coded on a day to day basis? One.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Notes from the talks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The future is being written in lines of code by Kathryn Parsons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t ask “can you be an engineer?” ask “are you creative? Persistent? Logical?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not that women aren’t capable of being developers, it’s that they’re opting out.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They’re dropping out of the roles they’re in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Girls aren’t choosing CS at schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Girls are far less confident that they’ll be able to engineer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talked about the importance of networking, and how women are often not included in traditional networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Art vs Science: why can’t we all just get along? with Nikki Durkin, Naomi Shepherd, Melanie Perkins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Art vs Science" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/panel-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discussion about how code is involved in creative endeavors - “code is a tool, just like a paint brush”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t ask “do you want to code?” ask “do you want to help people?” Clearly a common thread that “coding” is a turnoff for girls and women…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discussion around education

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to code through projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing education throughout your life - “never stop learning”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Questioning if a uni education is still valuable, and how it needs to change to stay up to date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;ABCs to CSS: solving the technology question with education with Ethy Levy, Dave Curran, Annie Parker, Verity Firth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ABCs to CSS" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/panel-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to code impacts other subjects as well. Teachers noticed better collaboration skills and students taking on problems on their own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things like Code Club (and CS First) are great for some kids, but it’s the Government&amp;#39;s job to make those things available to everyone - it’s slow work...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t wait for tech to be 50% women before joining in. Be the woman who takes it from 20% to 21%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The fashion technologist: solving the style question with technology with Amber Venz Box&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predicted tech trend: more “walled gardens” like instagram where the platform has the power - companies intentionally offering little functionality that’s very focused.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talked about work/life balance and having dedicated calendar time for being with her family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know your value and take it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The career disruption: reinvent your own career with Canna Campbell, Georgie Abay, Alyce Tran, Alice Brennan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two of the speakers started new businesses after leaving their previous roles and having children.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“What a waste not to be passionate about what you do for a living.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talked about having very unstructured days as founders and CEOs, but they always have some time dedicated to ideas and quiet working. This means having clear priorities is even more important for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Technology: why not women? With Aubrey Blanche, Anastasia Cammaroto, Alisa Bowen, Mikaela Jade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Why not women?" src="/images/blog/vogue-codes/panel-3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More discussion about tech’s “marketing problem” - mentioned advertising free beer more often than good parental leave policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brief vocab lesson:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sponsorship - using your network and clout to help someone once off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentorship - 1:1 long term help, building someone up and helping them grow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reverse mentorship - junior employees helping senior employees (typically for technical tasks the younger employees have more experience with)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small actions can make an overall change. Some suggestions:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take an hour a week to do sponsorship or mentorship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every few months (starting now) look at who you follow on Twitter. Are they all one gender, race, political view, sexual orientation, etc.? Rebalance to better represent society’s distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workshop for conference proposals</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/proposal-ideas-workshop/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/proposal-ideas-workshop/</id>
    <published>2016-02-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-19T19:32:28-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday I ran a workshop to help people come up with and refine conference talk ideas and then start working on a proposal for it. In preparation for the workshop I wrote a &lt;a href="/blog/2016/conference-proposal-ideas/"&gt;worksheet&lt;/a&gt; to help people come up with proposal ideas. This week I’ll write about the workshop and how you can run one as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workshop is ideal for beginners to run. All of the hard work is in the preparation, so you can take all the time you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need any special knowledge about conferences to run this workshop. If you happen to have conference proposal experience, all the better! But remember that it’s optional, so go for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If possible, find someone to help you with the workshop. They should be someone who has a lot of experience reviewing conference proposals, ideally they were on a selection committee recently. If you are writing your proposals for a specific conference then reach out to the organisers and let them know you’re going to run this workshop. Ask them if they can recommend anyone form the selection committee last year. When I’ve done this the organisers have always had at least one person to reach out to about helping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were able to find someone with reviewing experience then ask them to prepare a short (5-10 minute) talk for the workshop. Something like “Would you please give an overview of how the [Conference name here] process works, and how it&amp;#39;s similar and different to other conferences?” For my workshop this person was sick and wasn’t able to make it. The workshop still went smoothly, but I wasn’t able to give the attendees more information about how the selection process works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pick a casual space with chairs that move easily. As you’ll see, most of this workshop is moving around and bouncing ideas off people. It’s important to pick a space that facilitates this. Something like a university lecture hall wouldn’t be a good pick. Instead, choose somewhere that feels relaxed and makes moving around easy. Desks are handy, otherwise remind people to bring a notebook to press on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a projector is optional, but if there’s one handy I recommend it. I’ve included my &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/47z32c7gxjs9vws/cfp-workshop-public.key?dl=0"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; for you to use. There’s nothing particularly useful or mind blowing in it - mostly it’s full of timers to help people stay on track. It’s fine for you to keep track of the time on your laptop, but if you can have it up somewhere it makes it a bit easier on the participants to keep track of the time themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask attendees to bring a filled out copy of the ideas &lt;a href="/blog/2016/conference-proposal-ideas/"&gt;worksheet&lt;/a&gt;. This worksheet is their ticket - no worksheet, no workshop. Most of the workshop is bouncing ideas around and it’s not fair to the other attendees if someone doesn’t bring anything to the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Print out copies of the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/13DfiDw6rpasjq33ckGzqlLBrK59M2m6iQgyrv1IV_VM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BEfA3m4hP08o0-MOpeecJ5SuhU0LBjfFmuB-bErdveo/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;proposal worksheet&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BI7f7i3vI8vm4J47HoqDpB1OCRDfZPo5cUXMP8yHUgM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;accountability worksheet&lt;/a&gt; for everyone. It’s also a good idea to have some spare paper for people to write on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The workshop (1.5 - 2 hours)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so you’ve got your space, someone with selection experience, and your attendees all have their worksheets filled out - the hard part is done! Seriously, the actual workshop isn’t very much work on your part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things can get loud during this workshop, so be sure you’ve got a whistle, bell, or something that can make a lot of noise. I used bongo drums - it was awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is divided into two parts. The first part is on brainstorming and idea clarification. The second part is for coming up with a rough draft of the proposal. If you found them, your proposal selection expert goes in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Part 1 - speed dating (70 minutes)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this section people will pair up and discus their ideas. It’s important that everyone keeps switching pairs. I like to get people to move around a bit and get their blood flowing, so don’t ask them to pair up with the person next to them, instead pick something random (“find someone with the same first letter of your first name”). It’s silly, which is perfect - it gets people laughing, running around, and, most importantly, makes the whole workshop less serious and stressful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each pairing should discuss the ideas and decide which are the best ones. They should suggest ideas that are similar, places that would be good to give the talk, audiences who would be particularly interested, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have your proposal selection expert include them into this mix as well so they can be paired up with anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pair 1 (15 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time people pair up ask them to go through each of the questions on the worksheet one by one. So Person A talks about what ideas they came up with for question 1 then Person B goes through their answer, then they discuss.  Ideally they should end up with around &lt;strong&gt;five&lt;/strong&gt; ideas they want to keep pursing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pair 2 (12 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discuss the previous ideas and choose &lt;strong&gt;four&lt;/strong&gt; ideas to move forward with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pair 3 (9 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discuss the previous ideas and choose &lt;strong&gt;three&lt;/strong&gt; ideas to move forward with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pair 4 (6 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discuss the previous ideas and choose &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; ideas to move forward with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pair 5 (3 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discuss the previous ideas and choose &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; idea to move forward with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Group 1 (10 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask people to get into small groups (4-6 people per group). Have them discuss their final ideas and give feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Group 2 (15 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask people to get into large groups (about twenty people per group). Go around the room and say what each person&amp;#39;s idea is. It’s amazing to hear what people have come up with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Selection expert (5-15 minutes)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point ask your proposal selection helper to give their spiel. The move on to a (brief) time for questions, but don’t let it go on too long. Any questions like “what do you think of idea X” are banned - this is a time for big picture questions about the selection &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Part 2 - writing for the proposal (25 minutes)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Read the resources (5 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask everyone to read through the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/13DfiDw6rpasjq33ckGzqlLBrK59M2m6iQgyrv1IV_VM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt; on writing proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Fill out the proposal worksheet (5 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BEfA3m4hP08o0-MOpeecJ5SuhU0LBjfFmuB-bErdveo/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;proposal worksheet&lt;/a&gt; helps make an idea more concrete and focuses people’s thoughts on actually giving the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Bullet point rough draft (10 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to come up with a rough draft! This can be as messy as they want. Bullet points are fine - just take some time to get something on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Talk it through (3 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask people to pair up one more time. Have them talk through their proposal ideas and get some initial feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Accountability (2 minutes)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that same pair ask people to fill out the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BI7f7i3vI8vm4J47HoqDpB1OCRDfZPo5cUXMP8yHUgM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;accountability worksheet&lt;/a&gt;. It’s very easy to come up with an idea and never submit it - this worksheet is to help people commit and follow through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Done!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! You’ve done a whole workshop to help people come up with ideas, refine those ideas, and get started on a rough draft of a proposal. Fantastic job :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/47z32c7gxjs9vws/cfp-workshop-public.key?dl=0"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to write a proposal &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/13DfiDw6rpasjq33ckGzqlLBrK59M2m6iQgyrv1IV_VM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BEfA3m4hP08o0-MOpeecJ5SuhU0LBjfFmuB-bErdveo/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;Proposal worksheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BI7f7i3vI8vm4J47HoqDpB1OCRDfZPo5cUXMP8yHUgM/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;Accountability worksheet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to come up with conference proposal ideas</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/conference-proposal-ideas/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/conference-proposal-ideas/</id>
    <published>2016-02-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-24T17:47:41-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="hide-print"&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a conference coming up that you'd really like to speak at. The location is good, your boss is happy for you to take the time off, you’re excited to go. But you don’t have anything to say.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Been there? Me too. So have a lot of people. You’re not alone, promise! It’s an annoying place to be (especially if all your coworkers have lots of ideas...), but there are some things you can do to get your creative juices flowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="worksheet-instructions"&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Instructions&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Dedicate 30 minutes.&lt;/strong&gt; Start with just 30 minutes and decide how you feel. If you like the process, and think you’ve still got more ideas then keep going until you feel like you’re done. All I’m asking is that you commit to 30 minutes. That’s it. You can find half an hour at some point today or tomorrow. Go put it in your calendar now.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Print this page.&lt;/strong&gt; There’s something about writing on paper rather than a computer that helps my train of thought. &lt;span class="hide-print"&gt;Plus there's some sweet CSS on here to make it print well ;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Remove distractions.&lt;/strong&gt; Close your computer, set your phone to silent, and grab a pen or pencil. Computers and phones are really distracting. Any one of those notifications can easily break your flow and make you forget about that idea you just started.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Think about the conference.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are applying to a particular conference consider what topics are relevant and who is likely to attend. Some topics you come up with will be relevant and some won’t. That’s ok! As you go through the worksheet keep coming back to the conference to see if you can come up with any more ideas that are on point. Don’t discount the other ideas though!
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Answer the questions in whatever order you feel like.&lt;/strong&gt; If you get inspired at any point, that’s awesome and should be rewarded. If you don’t feel like answering a particular one, skip it. The questions are there as prompts, and shouldn’t feel prescriptive. If you come up with an idea that doesn’t fit into the prompts write it down in the “Other” section. If you come up with another question prompt please tell me so I can update the worksheet!
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Write without censoring.&lt;/strong&gt; This step is the hardest and most important. Remember, you never have to share any of these ideas with anyone. All you need to do is write them down. (But I hope you choose to share them!) It doesn’t matter if you don’t think it’s good, or if everyone already knows about it, or if it’s boring, just put something down.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Please take these steps seriously. I worked hard to put this worksheet together, now it’s your turn to work hard and fill it up :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="page-break"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="worksheet-questions"&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s something you work with fairly regularly and understand 80% of, but not 100%?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s a new technology or technique that you’ve heard of recently, but don’t know much about?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Do you have a particular workflow that you use and really like?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s an accepted practice that “everyone knows” but that you (or others) haven’t looked into for a while?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s your hobby? What lessons are shared between your hobby and your job?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;div class="page-break"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Think back to a year ago. What would you have wanted to know? What advice would you need?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s a book you read or an experience you had recently that you found particularly interesting, relevant, or profound?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;What’s a talk you’d want to see at this conference? Perhaps it’s on a technology you’re interested in, or a non-technical topic you’ve wondered or struggled with recently.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Is there something that irritates you about your work or process? How could it be solved? Perhaps you’ve solved it already and can share your story, or perhaps you need to do some research first.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;div class="page-break"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Think of a problem you’ve had in the past month or two.
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;If you did solve it, how did you solve it? Were there other ways you could have solved it? Why did you pick the way that you did?&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;If you came across the same problem again, what would you have done differently?&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;If you didn’t solve it, what went wrong? How could others avoid it in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
                &lt;hr&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Are there any talks you would enjoy giving? It can be on any topic and aimed at any audience.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Write out a bunch of adjectives and nouns about yourself. Also jot down various things you’ve done. Play around with some of those words and history and see if you can find a talk in the overlap. (For example I’m a programmer, baker, and I’ve run a few study groups. I might come up with how does baking relate to programming? Or how can programmers continue learning with study groups?)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Other&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="follow-up"&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Follow up&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Great job! You spent 30 minutes brainstorming possible talk ideas, that’s a massive step forward - high five! (But if you didn’t spend 30 minutes and have instead skimmed this page then no high five for you!)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Like I said, that’s everything I asked you to commit to. You’re off the hook. If you have &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; down on your worksheet then I give you permission to say that you “don’t have anything to say.”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;But. If you’ve got one thing written down, then you’ve got something to say. Then it’s time to move on to the next phase of proposal writing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="hide-print"&gt;
  &lt;h2&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This worksheet came about because of the encouraging words of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Sthreo"&gt;Esther Asenjo&lt;/a&gt; - “Oh you have a lot of things to say! It's just you forgot they are interesting.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The questions started from a workshop ran by Rosemary and John Allsopp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Programming theory: Evaluation strategies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2015/programming-theory-evaluation-strategies/"/>
    <id>http://lucybain.com/blog/2015/programming-theory-evaluation-strategies/</id>
    <published>2015-11-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-14T17:42:56-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a topic I learned at university, but didn’t fully understand all the repercussions of until later. This post is to help you understand the differences and to help me remember them :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But wait, what’s an “evaluation strategy”? I’ve never heard of that before!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I hadn’t either until I did some research for this post. The title for this group of concepts isn’t widely used, so knowing “evaluation strategy” probably won’t be super useful. However, the question all evaluation strategies are trying to answer is “how do parameters work in this particular language?” And it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; useful to know the answer to that question for your language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this non-language below (which is purposefully a mismatch of ruby, python, and JS so it doesn’t look real):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;a = 1

function passBySomething(param):
    param = 2
end

passBySomething(a)
log(a) // what happens here?
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few options that could happen, which is what today’s post is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I love metaphors and because we haven’t talked about how computer memory works yet (although it might show up soon!) we won’t cover “under the hood” details. Instead we will work with a story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you look around your apartment you decide you would like some new artwork to spruce the place up a bit. As it so happens you have a nice piece of canvas at home, all ready to go. You also have a friend, Fred, who is an artist and who’s agreed to make you something (that you’ll pay for, of course!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind we’re ready to go! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; Because we’re not going into the details, nor are we looking at a particular language, these explanations might not apply 100% to your language. Please look up additional examples for your language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pass by reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give your canvas to Fred and &lt;strong&gt;he paints it for you&lt;/strong&gt; (thanks Fred!). Then he gives you the painted canvas back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the easiest one to get our heads around, since it’s pretty much what happens in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what pass by reference would be in our pretend language:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (this is a blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    paint(item) // notice the lack of return keyword
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas)
log(canvas) // [*&amp;amp;] (painted canvas)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems straight forward enough, but what if Fred decides to do something different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give your canvas to Fred and &lt;strong&gt;he makes a sculpture instead&lt;/strong&gt;. Then he gives you the sculpture back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this translates to the following “code”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    item = new Sculpture()
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas)
log(canvas) // V (new sculpture)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you don’t have your original canvas (Fred replaced it entirely), you only have the sculpture Fred gave you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pass by reference is incredibly trusting. You like Fred, and he’s a really good artist. If he says a sculpture would be better for your space you’re cool to go with that. If he paints the whole canvas one colour and tells you it’s art, you’ll believe him and put it up with pride. After all, Fred’s a good guy and you trust him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;More formal definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pass by reference the original variable (declared outside the function’s scope) can be changed in any way by the function. It can be altered or reassigned in the function and the new value will persist after the function has returned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pass by value&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You go to the store and buy a new piece of canvas that is exactly the same as the one you already own. You give the new canvas to Fred and &lt;strong&gt;he paints it for you&lt;/strong&gt; (thanks Fred!). Then he gives you the painted canvas back, and you can choose to replace your blank canvas with the painted one, keep both, or just look at Fred’s work and decide not to keep it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our pretend coding language it would look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    return paint(item) // notice the new return keyword
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas) // look at the Fred’s work but decide not to keep it
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)

newCanvas = artistFred(canvas) // keep both
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
log(newCanvas) // [*&amp;amp;] (painted canvas)

canvas = artistFred(canvas) // replace blank canvas with the painted one
log(canvas) // [*&amp;amp;] (painted canvas)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Fred might decide to do something else entirely. Let’s look at another possibility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You go to the store and buy a new piece of canvas that is exactly the same as the one you already own. You give the new canvas to Fred, but he throws away the new canvas and &lt;strong&gt;decides to make a sculpture instead.&lt;/strong&gt; Then he gives you the sculpture back, and you can choose to replace your blank canvas with the sculpture, keep both, or just look at Fred’s work and decide not to keep it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, in our fake language would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    item = new Sculpture()
    return item
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas) // look at the Fred’s work but decide not to keep it
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)

newSculpture = artistFred(canvas) // keep both
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
log(newSculpture) // V (sculpture)

canvas = artistFred(canvas) // replace blank canvas with the sculpture
log(canvas) // V (sculpture)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think of pass by value as slightly paranoid. Because really, you don’t trust Fred very much. You think he might make an ugly painting and you want to keep your piece of canvas safe in case that happens. Or you know he doesn’t follow directions well and you didn’t want that sculpture anyway...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;More formal definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pass by value the original variable (declared outside the function’s scope) is not altered in any way by the function. It must be explicitly overwritten by reassigning it with the results of the function call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pass by sharing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bit of a mix between pass by reference and pass by value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give your (only) canvas to Fred and &lt;strong&gt;he paints it for you&lt;/strong&gt; (thanks Fred!). Then he gives you the painted canvas back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far this is exactly the same as pass by reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    paint(item)
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas)
log(canvas) // [*&amp;amp;] (painted canvas)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again, Fred might decide to do something different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give your (only) canvas to Fred. He sets the untouched canvas aside and &lt;strong&gt;makes a sculpture instead&lt;/strong&gt;. Then he gives you the sculpture back, and you can choose to replace your blank canvas with the sculpture, keep both, or just look at Fred’s work and decide not to keep it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;canvas = [] // (blank canvas)

function artistFred(item):
    item = new Sculpture()
    return item
end

log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
artistFred(canvas) // look at the Fred’s work but decide not to keep it
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)

newSculpture = artistFred(canvas) // keep both
log(canvas) // [] (blank canvas)
log(newSculpture) // V (sculpture)

canvas = artistFred(canvas) // replace blank canvas with the painted one
log(canvas) // V (sculpture)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version is exactly the same as pass by value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most reasonable level of trust. You asked for a painting and a sculpture just won’t do. You trust Fred enough to paint a blank canvas, but you want your canvas to be usable if he decided to go off an make a sculpture instead. After all, you asked for a painting, not a sculpture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What gives? How can you mix and match like that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all depends on if the canvas is altered or replaced. If Fred simply alters the canvas by painting it, then the original (blank) canvas is changed forever. However, if Fred wants to replace the canvas, he can’t throw it away, but must create a sculpture as an entirely new thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;More formal definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pass by sharing the original variable (declared outside the function’s scope) can only be altered in so far as it is mutable. It cannot be reassigned inside the function call. Any changes to a mutable type will persist after the function returns. Any attempts to reassign a variable will not persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;And one more thing...&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People use the wrong name all. the. time. Officially most languages use pass by sharing. Per &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evaluation_strategy#Call_by_sharing"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is used by languages such as Python, Iota, Java (for object references), Ruby, JavaScript, Scheme, OCaml, AppleScript, and many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, most people don’t say a particular language is “pass by sharing.” Unfortuantely “pass by reference” and “pass by value” are much more famous phrases than “pass by sharing” (probably because it’s what we’re taught at universities), and so people often use one of those terms even when it’s incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This semantic mixing caused me a fair amount of confusion because JS shows some pass by reference qualities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;var obj = {a: 1};

function referenceTest(input) {
    input.a = 2;
}

console.log(obj); // logs {a: 1}
referenceTest(obj);
console.log(obj); // logs {a: 2}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and some pass by value qualities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight plaintext"&gt;var num = 1;

function valueTest(input) {
    input = 1;
}

console.log(num); // logs 1
valueTest(num);
console.log(num); // logs 1
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a long time to realise that JS was pass by reference &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt; and pass by value &lt;em&gt;other times&lt;/em&gt;. And I only learned today that this mix of of the two, which many common languages use, is called pass by sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evaluation_strategy"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/518000/is-javascript-a-pass-by-reference-or-pass-by-value-language"&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples and explanation for &lt;a href="https://www.jeffknupp.com/blog/2012/11/13/is-python-callbyvalue-or-callbyreference-neither/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
